Well this is a really extraordinary honor for me.
حسناً هذا شرفٌ عظيمٌ لي.
I spend most of my time
لقد قضيت معظم حياتي
in jails, in prisons, on death row.
في السجون ، والمعتقلات ، وبين المحكوم عليهم بالإعدام.
I spend most of my time in very low-income communities
قضيت معظم حياتي بين المجتمعات ذات الدخل المحدود
in the projects and places where there's a great deal of hopelessness.
في المشروعات والأماكن التي يسكنها الكثير من اليأس والإحباط
And being here at TED
وكوني هنا في تيد "TED"
and seeing the stimulation, hearing it,
أشاهد التحفيز ، وأسمعه ،
has been very, very energizing to me.
قد كان لي محفزاً قوياً جداً.
And one of the things that's emerged in my short time here
وأحد الأشياء التي لآحظتها خلال فترتي القصيرة هنا
is that TED has an identity.
هو أن مؤتمر تيد لديه هوية.
And you can actually say things here
وأن بإمكاننا قول أشياء هنا
that have impacts around the world.
قد يكون لها أثراً في جميع أنحاء العالم.
And sometimes when it comes through TED,
وأحياناً عندما تكون مقدمةً عبر منصة تيد ،
it has meaning and power
يكون لديها وقعٌ وصدى أكبر
that it doesn't have when it doesn't.
مما لو أتت من خارج تيد.
And I mention that because I think identity is really important.
وأذكر هذا لأنني أعتقد أن الهوية شيءٌ مهمٌ للغاية.
And we've had some fantastic presentations.
وقد شاهدنا أفكاراً رائعة من خلال النقاشات.
And I think what we've learned
وأعتقد بأننا تعلمنا
is that, if you're a teacher your words can be meaningful,
أنه ، إذا كنت معلماً ، فإن كلماتك لها معنى ،
but if you're a compassionate teacher,
ولكن إذا كنت معلماً حنوناً،
they can be especially meaningful.
فستكون كلماتك ذات معنىً خاص.
If you're a doctor you can do some good things,
وإذا كنت طبيباً ، فبإمكانك عمل أشياء جيدة ،
but if you're a caring doctor you can do some other things.
ولكن إذا كنت طبيباً متعاطفاً فستقوم بعمل أشياء أفضل.
And so I want to talk about the power of identity.
لذا ، أود الحديث عن قوة الهوية.
And I didn't learn about this actually
و فعلياً لم أتعلم هذا
practicing law and doing the work that I do.
أثناء ممارستي للمحاماة من خلال عملي.
I actually learned about this from my grandmother.
ولكن تعلمت هذا من جدتي.
I grew up in a house
لقد تربيت في بيتٍ تقليدي
that was the traditional African-American home
ذات طابع أمريكي من أصول أفريقية
that was dominated by a matriarch,
والذي تحكمه الأم ،
and that matriarch was my grandmother.
وتلك الأم الحاكمة كانت جدتي.
She was tough, she was strong,
كانت صعبةً ، قويةً ،
she was powerful.
وكانت مسيطرة.
She was the end of every argument in our family.
كانت لها الكلمة النهائية في أي جدلٍ في العائلة.
She was the beginning of a lot of arguments in our family.
وكانت هي من تبدأ الكثير من الجدل في العائلة.
She was the daughter of people who were actually enslaved.
كانت ابنةً لعائلةٍ مستعبدة.
Her parents were born in slavery in Virginia in the 1840's.
فأبواها كانا قد ولدا في العبودية في فيرجينيا خلال فترة ١٨٤٠.
She was born in the 1880's
وولدت هي في فترة ١٨٨٠
and the experience of slavery
وتجربة العبودية بصفةٍ خاصة
very much shaped the way she saw the world.
شكّلت الطريقة التي من خلالها نظرت إلى العالم.
And my grandmother was tough, but she was also loving.
فكانت جدتي صعبةً ، ولكنها أيضاً كانت محبة.
When I would see her as a little boy,
وكنت عندما أقابلها كطفلٍ صغير ،
she'd come up to me and she'd give me these hugs.
كانت تأتي نحوي وتضمني.
And she'd squeeze me so tight I could barely breathe
وتضغط علي في الضم حتى بالكاد أتنفس
and then she'd let me go.
ومن ثم تدعني أذهب.
And an hour or two later, if I saw her,
وبعد ساعةٍ أو اثنين لاحقاً ، إذا قابلتها ،
she'd come over to me and she'd say, "Bryan, do you still feel me hugging you?"
تأتي نحوي وتقول : " بريان : هل لازلت تحس بضمتي لك ؟ "
And if I said, "No," she'd assault me again,
وإذا قلت : " لا "، ستهجم علي مرةً أخرى ،
and if I said, "Yes," she'd leave me alone.
وإذا قلت : "نعم" ، تتركني وشأني.
And she just had this quality
كانت لديها تلك الجاذبية
that you always wanted to be near her.
بحيث أنك تريد دائماً أن تكون بالقرب منها.
And the only challenge was that she had 10 children.
والمشكلة الوحيدة هي أنه كان لديها عشرة أطفال.
My mom was the youngest of her 10 kids.
وأمي كانت أصغر الأطفال العشرة.
And sometimes when I would go and spend time with her,
وأحياناً عندما أذهب لقضاء الوقت معها ،
it would be difficult to get her time and attention.
يكون علي من الصعب الحصول على انتباهها ووقتها.
My cousins would be running around everywhere.
فأبناء الخالات يكونون منتشرين في جميع الأنحاء.
And I remember, when I was about eight or nine years old,
وأذكر ، أنني عندما كنت في عمر الثامنة أو التاسعة ،
waking up one morning, going into the living room,
استيقظت في الصباح ، واتجهت إلى غرفة المعيشة ،
and all of my cousins were running around.
وكان كل أبناء عمي يلعبون في المكان.
And my grandmother was sitting across the room
وكانت جدتي تجلس في طرف الغرفة
staring at me.
تراقبني.
And at first I thought we were playing a game.
وفي بداية الأمر إعتقدت أننا نلعب لعبةً ما.
And I would look at her and I'd smile,
فكنت أنظر إليها وأبتسم ،
but she was very serious.
ولكنها بدت جديةً جداً.
And after about 15 or 20 minutes of this,
وبعد حوالي ١٥ أو ٢٠ دقيقة ،
she got up and she came across the room
نهضت واتجهت نحوي
and she took me by the hand
وأخذت بيدي
and she said, "Come on, Bryan. You and I are going to have a talk."
ثم قالت : " تعال يا بريان ، أنا وأنت سنتحدث قليلاً."
And I remember this just like it happened yesterday.
وأتذكر هذا ، كما لو أنه البارحة.
I never will forget it.
لن أنساه أبداً.
She took me out back and she said, "Bryan, I'm going to tell you something,
أخذتني إلى الخارج وقالت : " بريان ، سأخبرك بشيء ،
but you don't tell anybody what I tell you."
ولكن لاتخبر أحداً بما سأقوله لك."
I said, "Okay, Mama."
فقلت : " حسناً ، جدتي"
She said, "Now you make sure you don't do that." I said, "Sure."
فقالت : " عليك أن تكون حريصاً ألا تخبر أحداً." ، فقلت : "بالتأكيد"
Then she sat me down and she looked at me
ثم أجلستني ونظرت إلي
and she said, "I want you to know
وقالت : " أريدك أن تعرف
I've been watching you."
أنني كنت أراقبك."
And she said, "I think you're special."
ثم قالت : " وأعتقد بأنك شخصٌ مميز"
She said, "I think you can do anything you want to do."
وقالت : " وأعتقد أنه بإمكانك فعل أي شيءٍ تريد فعله."
I will never forget it.
لن أنسى ذلك أبداً.
And then she said, "I just need you to promise me three things, Bryan."
ثم قالت : " ولكن أريدك أن تعدني بثلاثة أشياء ، بريان."
I said, "Okay, Mama."
فقلت : " حسناً ، جدتي"
She said, "The first thing I want you to promise me
فقالت : " أول شيءٍ أريدك أن تعدني به هو
is that you'll always love your mom."
أن تحب أمك دائماً"
She said, "That's my baby girl,
قالت : " إنها طفلتي ،
and you have to promise me now you'll always take care of her."
وعليك أن تعدني الآن بأنك دائماً ستعتني بها."
Well I adored my mom, so I said, "Yes, Mama. I'll do that."
حسناً ، بالطبع كنت أحب أمي كثيراً فقلت : " نعم ، جدتي سأفعل ذلك"
Then she said, "The second thing I want you to promise me
ثم قالت : " والشيء الآخر أريدك أن تعدني به
is that you'll always do the right thing
هو أنك دائماً ستفعل الشيء الصائب
even when the right thing is the hard thing."
حتى عندما يكون فعل الصواب هو الشيء الأصعب."
And I thought about it and I said, "Yes, Mama. I'll do that."
وفكرت بذلك ثم قلت : " نعم ، جدتي. سأفعل ذلك."
Then finally she said, "The third thing I want you to promise me
وأخيراً قالت : " والشيء الثالث الذي أريدك أن تعدني به
is that you'll never drink alcohol."
هو أن لا تشرب الكحول أبداً."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Well I was nine years old, so I said, "Yes, Mama. I'll do that."
حسناً كنت في عمر التاسعة ، لذا قلت :" نعم ، جدتي. سأفعل ذلك."
I grew up in the country in the rural South,
لقد كبرت في ريفٍ في الجنوب ،
and I have a brother a year older than me and a sister a year younger.
وكان لدي أخ يكبرني بسنة وأخت تصغرني بسنة.
When I was about 14 or 15,
وعندما بلغت ال ١٤ أو الـ ١٥
one day my brother came home and he had this six-pack of beer --
عاد أخي إلى البيت ومعه ست زجاجاتٍ من البيرة --
I don't know where he got it --
لا أدري من أين أحضرها --
and he grabbed me and my sister and we went out in the woods.
وأخذني أنا وأختي وذهبنا إلى الخارج بين الأشجار.
And we were kind of just out there doing the stuff we crazily did.
وكنا دائماً ما نفعل أشياء مجنونةٍ هناك.
And he had a sip of this beer and he gave some to my sister and she had some,
وأخذ رشفةً من تلك البيرة
and they offered it to me.
وعرضوها علي.
I said, "No, no, no. That's okay. You all go ahead. I'm not going to have any beer."
فقلت : "لا ، لا ، لا. لا بأس. تفضلوا أنتم. لن أتناول البيرة أبداً."
My brother said, "Come on. We're doing this today; you always do what we do.
فقال أخي : "هيا. إننا نفعل هذا اليوم. ودائماً ما تفعل مثلما نفعل نحن.
I had some, your sister had some. Have some beer."
لقد تناولت البعض ، وأختك تناولت بعضاً منه ، وجاء دورك الآن."
I said, "No, I don't feel right about that. Y'all go ahead. Y'all go ahead."
قلت: "لا ، لا أشعر بالراحة في فعل ذلك. لكن بإمكانكم تناوله ، تفضلوا."
And then my brother started staring at me.
و بعد ذلك بدأ أخي بالتحديق بي.
He said, "What's wrong with you? Have some beer."
وقال: "مالذي أصابك ؟ تناول بعضاً من البيرة."
Then he looked at me real hard and he said,
ثم نظر إلي بشدةٍ وقال:
"Oh, I hope you're not still hung up
" أوه ، أتمنى ألا تكون لازلت متمسكاً
on that conversation Mama had with you."
بذلك الحديث التي حدثتك به جدتي."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I said, "Well, what are you talking about?"
فقلت : "حسناً ، مالذي تتحدث عنه ؟ "
He said, "Oh, Mama tells all the grandkids that they're special."
فقال: " أوه ، جدتي تخبر كل أحفادها أنهم مميزون."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I was devastated.
فأصابني الإحباط.
And I'm going to admit something to you.
وسأعترف لكم بشيء.
I'm going to tell you something I probably shouldn't.
سأخبركم بشيءٍ ليس من المفترض أن أخبركم به.
I know this might be broadcast broadly.
لأنني أعلم بأن هذا سينتشر إعلامياً.
But I'm 52 years old,
ولكنني أبلغ من العمر ٥٢ سنةً.
and I'm going to admit to you
وسأعترف لكم
that I've never had a drop of alcohol.
بأنني لم أتناول قطرةً واحدةً من الكحول.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I don't say that because I think that's virtuous;
ولا أقول هذا لكونه شيئآً أخلاقياً فاضلاً.
I say that because there is power in identity.
ولكنني أقوله لأن فيه تميزٌ للهوية.
When we create the right kind of identity,
عندما نقوم بخلق هوية ما،
we can say things to the world around us
نستطيع قول أشياء للناس من حولنا
that they don't actually believe makes sense.
لم يكونوا ليقتنعوا بها لولا ذلك الشيء.
We can get them to do things
ونقنعهم بعمل أشياء
that they don't think they can do.
لم يكونوا ليقتنعوا بأنهم قادرون على عملها.
When I thought about my grandmother,
عندما فكرت بجدتي ،
of course she would think all her grandkids were special.
بالطبع كانت تعتقد بأن جميع أحفادها مميزون.
My grandfather was in prison during prohibition.
فجدي كان في السجن في فترة حظر الكحوليات.
My male uncles died of alcohol-related diseases.
وأعمامي توفوا بسبب أمراض متعلقة بالكحوليات.
And these were the things she thought we needed to commit to.
وكانت تلك هي الأشياء التي اعتقدت جدتي علينا تفاديها.
Well I've been trying to say something
حسناً كنت أريد التحدث عن
about our criminal justice system.
النظام القضائي لدينا.
This country is very different today
فهذه البلد مختلفةٌ تماماً اليوم
than it was 40 years ago.
عما كانت عليه قبل ٤٠ سنة.
In 1972, there were 300,000 people in jails and prisons.
ففي ١٩٧٢ ، كان هناك ٣٠٠.٠٠٠ سجين.
Today, there are 2.3 million.
واليوم هناك ٢،٣ مليون سجين.
The United States now has the highest rate of incarceration
الولايات المتحدة لديها أعلى معدل في عدد المساجين
in the world.
على مستوى العالم.
We have seven million people on probation and parole.
لدينا سبعة ملايين شخص تحت المراقبة والإفراج المشروط.
And mass incarceration, in my judgment,
و ضخامة عدد المساجين ، في إعتقادي
has fundamentally changed our world.
غيّرت جذرياً عالمنا.
In poor communities, in communities of color
ففي المجتمعات الفقيرة ، ذات الأصول العرقية الملونة
there is this despair,
هناك إحباط ،
there is this hopelessness,
هناك ذلك اليأس ،
that is being shaped by these outcomes.
الذي تشكل نتيجة تلك المعطيات.
One out of three black men
فواحد من بين كل ثلاثة رجال سود
between the ages of 18 and 30
في الأعمار مابين ١٨ و ٣٠
is in jail, in prison, on probation or parole.
في السجن ، أو الحجز ، أو تحت الإفراج المشروط.
In urban communities across this country --
في مناطق المجتمعات المتمدنة في هذه البلاد --
Los Angeles, Philadelphia, Baltimore, Washington --
لوس أنجلس ، فيلادلفيا ، بالتيمور ، واشنطن --
50 to 60 percent of all young men of color are
من ٥٠ إلى ٦٠ بالمائة من الشباب من الأعراق الملونة
in jail or prison or on probation or parole.
في السجن أو الحجز أو تحت الإفراج المشروط.
Our system isn't just being shaped
فنظامنا لا يتشكل فقط
in these ways that seem to be distorting around race,
بتلك الطريقة المشوهه للأعراق فقط ،
they're also distorted by poverty.
بل أيضاً بحسب الفقر.
We have a system of justice in this country
لدينا نظامٌ قضائي في هذه البلد
that treats you much better
يعاملك بطريقةٍ أفضل
if you're rich and guilty than if you're poor and innocent.
عندما تكون ثرياً مذنباً مما لو كنت فقيراً بريئاً.
Wealth, not culpability,
الثراء ، وليس الذنب ،
shapes outcomes.
يُشكل النتائج.
And yet, we seem to be very comfortable.
ومع هذا ، نبدوا وكأننا معتادين لذلك.
The politics of fear and anger
فسياسة الخوف والغضب
have made us believe
جعلتنا نعتقد
that these are problems that are not our problems.
بأن تلك المشاكل لا تعنينا.
We've been disconnected.
فنحن منعزلون.
It's interesting to me.
ومايثير إهتمامي.
We're looking at some very interesting developments in our work.
هو أننا سنشهد تطورات مهمة في عملنا.
My state of Alabama, like a number of states,
ففي ولايتي آلاباما ، كالكثير من الولايات ،
actually permanently disenfranchises you
تحرمك من حقوقك إلى الأبد
if you have a criminal conviction.
إذا كان لديك سابقةٌ جنائية.
Right now in Alabama
الآن في آلاباما
34 percent of the black male population
٣٤ بالمائة من السكان الذكور السود
has permanently lost the right to vote.
فقدوا حقهم في الإنتخاب إلى الأبد.
We're actually projecting in another 10 years
ونتوقع أنه في العشر سنواتٍ القادمة
the level of disenfranchisement
مستوى الحرمان من الحقوق
will be as high as it's been
سيكون مرتفعاً بالمستوى الذي كان عليه
since prior to the passage of the Voting Rights Act.
قبل إقرار قانون حقوق التصويت للسود.
And there is this stunning silence.
ومع ذلك فهناك ذلك الصمت المدهش.
I represent children.
إنني أُمثل الأطفال.
A lot of my clients are very young.
فالكثير من زبائني صغار السن.
The United States is the only country in the world
والولايات المتحدة هي الدولة الوحيدة في العالم
where we sentence 13-year-old children
التي تحكم على طفلٍ بعمر ١٣ سنة
to die in prison.
بالحكم المؤبد.
We have life imprisonment without parole for kids in this country.
لدينا أحكام بالمؤبد بدون إطلاق سراح في هذه البلاد.
And we're actually doing some litigation.
وفي الحقيقة لدينا دعوى بخصوص هذا الشأن.
The only country in the world.
الدولة الوحيدة في العالم.
I represent people on death row.
أُمثل أناساً في قائمة الإعدام.
It's interesting, this question of the death penalty.
وهذا مثيرٌ للإهتمام ، هذا الحكم بالإعدام.
In many ways, we've been taught to think
تعلمنا بشتى الطرق في التفكير
that the real question is,
في أن السؤال الحقيقي هو :
do people deserve to die for the crimes they've committed?
هل يستحق الناس أن يعدموا لجرائم إرتكبوها ؟
And that's a very sensible question.
وهذا سؤالٌ حسّاسٌ جداً.
But there's another way of thinking
ولكن هناك طريقةٌ أخرى للتفكير في ذلك
about where we are in our identity.
لمعرفة أين وصلنا بهويتنا.
The other way of thinking about it
والطريقة الأخرى للتفكير بذلك
is not, do people deserve to die for the crimes they commit,
ليست ما إذا كان الشخص يستحق الموت لجرمٍ إرتكبه ،
but do we deserve to kill?
ولكن هل نملك الحق في القتل ؟
I mean, it's fascinating.
أعني ، هذا مذهل.
Death penalty in America is defined by error.
الحكم بالإعدام في أمريكا معروفٌ بالأخطاء.
For every nine people who have been executed,
فمن بين كل تسعة أشخاص مُعدَمين ،
we've actually identified one innocent person
تمكّنا من تحديد شخص بريء
who's been exonerated and released from death row.
تمت تبرأته وإنقاذه من الإعدام.
A kind of astonishing error rate --
إنه معدل خطأٍ مرعب --
one out of nine people innocent.
شخصٌ بريء من بين كل تسعة أشخاص.
I mean, it's fascinating.
أعني ، هذا غريب.
In aviation, we would never let people fly on airplanes
ففي الطيران ، لن نسمح للناس بالطيران
if for every nine planes that took off
إذا كان هناك طائرةً تسقط من بين
one would crash.
كل تسع طائرات.
But somehow we can insulate ourselves from this problem.
ولكن بطريقةٍ ما نستطيع عزل أنفسنا عن هذه المشكلة.
It's not our problem.
إنها ليست مشكلتنا.
It's not our burden.
إنها ليست معاناتنا.
It's not our struggle.
إنه ليس صراعنا.
I talk a lot about these issues.
وأنا أتحدث دائماً عن تلك المواضيع
I talk about race and this question
أتحدث عن العنصرية وعن ذلك السؤال
of whether we deserve to kill.
ما إذا كنا نملك الحق في القتل.
And it's interesting, when I teach my students about African-American history,
وهذا مثير ، عندما أدرس تلاميذي عن تاريخ الأميركيين من الأصول الأفريقية ،
I tell them about slavery.
أُحدثهم عن العبودية.
I tell them about terrorism,
أُحدثهم عن الإرهاب ،
the era that began at the end of reconstruction
الفترة التي تلت نهاية عصر البناء
that went on to World War II.
والتي استمرت حتى الحرب العالمية الثانية.
We don't really know very much about it.
والتي بالفعل لانعلم الكثير عنها.
But for African-Americans in this country,
ولكن بالنسبة للأمريكيين من أصول أفريقية في هذا البلد ،
that was an era defined by terror.
كانت تلك الفترة هي فترة الإرهاب.
In many communities, people had to worry about being lynched.
في مجتمعي ، كان الناس يخافون من أن يُعدَموا.
They had to worry about being bombed.
وكانوا يخافون من أن يتم قصفَهُم.
It was the threat of terror that shaped their lives.
التهديد بالإرهاب هو ماشكّلَ حياتهم.
And these older people come up to me now
وهؤلاء الناس الكبار في السن يأتون إلي اليوم
and they say, "Mr. Stevenson, you give talks, you make speeches,
ويقولون : " مستر ستيفنسون ، عندما تتحدث ، عندما تقدم خطاباً ،
you tell people to stop saying
عليك أن تنبه الناس ألّا يقولوا
we're dealing with terrorism for the first time in our nation's history
أننا نتعامل مع الإرهاب لأول مرة في تاريخنا
after 9/11."
بعد أحداث ٩/١١"
They tell me to say, "No, tell them that we grew up with that."
يطلبون مني أن أقول : " لا ، أخبرهم بأننا كَبُرنا تحت وطأة الإرهاب."
And that era of terrorism, of course,
وتلك الفترة من الإرهاب ، بالطبع ،
was followed by segregation
قد تلتها فترة الفصل العنصري
and decades of racial subordination
وعقود من التبعية العنصرية
and apartheid.
والتمييز.
And yet, we have in this country this dynamic
وبعد كل هذا ، لدينا في هذا البلد ذلك الإنشغال
where we really don't like to talk about our problems.
بحيث لا نحب أن نتحدث عن مشاكلنا تلك.
We don't like to talk about our history.
لا نحب الحديث عن تاريخنا.
And because of that, we really haven't understood
وبسبب ذلك ، فنحن فعلياً لم نفهم
what it's meant to do the things we've done historically.
مدى تأثير ما فعلناه بتاريخنا.
We're constantly running into each other.
نحن نقع في مشاكل مع بعضنا باستمرار.
We're constantly creating tensions and conflicts.
ونخلق فتراتٍ من التوتر والنزاعات.
We have a hard time talking about race,
ولدينا مشكلةً عصيبة في التحدث عن العنصرية ،
and I believe it's because we are unwilling to commit ourselves
وأعتقد أن ذلك لأننا غير مستعدين للإلتزام
to a process of truth and reconciliation.
بمراحل منهجية من الإعتراف بالحقيقة ومن ثم المصالحة.
In South Africa, people understood
في جنوب أفريقيا ، فهم الناس
that we couldn't overcome apartheid
أنه لا يمكنهم مواجهة التمييز
without a commitment to truth and reconciliation.
من دون الإلتزام بالإعتراف بالحقيقة والمصالحة.
In Rwanda, even after the genocide, there was this commitment,
وفي رواندا ، حتى بعد الإبادة الجماعية ، كان هناك إلتزام ،
but in this country we haven't done that.
ولكن في هذا البلد فنحن لم نفعل ذلك.
I was giving some lectures in Germany about the death penalty.
كنت أُعطي بعض المحاضرات في ألمانيا عن عقوبة الإعدام.
It was fascinating
وكانت مذهلة
because one of the scholars stood up after the presentation
لأن أحد العلماء وقف بعد المحاضرة
and said, "Well you know it's deeply troubling
وقال : " حسناً أتعلم أن ما سمعناك تتحدث عنه
to hear what you're talking about."
مزعجٌ للغاية بالنسبة لنا."
He said, "We don't have the death penalty in Germany.
وقال : " ليس لدينا عقوبة الإعدام هنا في ألمانيا.
And of course, we can never have the death penalty in Germany."
وبالطبع ، لن نسمح بعقوبة الإعدام في ألمانيا بتاتاً "
And the room got very quiet,
فأصبحت القاعة هادئةً تماماً ،
and this woman said,
ثم قالت إحداهن :
"There's no way, with our history,
"لا يمكن بأي حالٍ من الأحوال ، في تاريخنا ،
we could ever engage
أن نشترك
in the systematic killing of human beings.
في القتل المنظم للبشر.
It would be unconscionable for us
سيكون ذلك غير أخلاقيٍ بالنسبة لنا
to, in an intentional and deliberate way,
أن نشترك بتعمد و بطريقةٍ مقصودة
set about executing people."
في إعدام البشر."
And I thought about that.
وفكرت في ذلك.
What would it feel like
كيف سيكون شعور
to be living in a world
العيش في عالمٍ
where the nation state of Germany was executing people,
لو أن الأمة الألمانية كانت تُعدم الناس ،
especially if they were disproportionately Jewish?
خاصةً لو أنهم يهود غير لائقين ؟
I couldn't bear it.
لم أستطع تخيل ذلك.
It would be unconscionable.
سيكون ذلك غير أخلاقي.
And yet, in this country,
وبالرغم من ذلك ، في هذا البلد ،
in the states of the Old South,
في ولايات الجنوب القديمة ،
we execute people --
لا زلنا نعدم الناس --
where you're 11 times more likely to get the death penalty
بحيث أن احتمال أن تلقى عقوبة الإعدام يتضاعف ١١ مرة
if the victim is white than if the victim is black,
إذا كانت الضحية من العرق الأبيض مما لوكانت من العرق الأسود ،
22 times more likely to get it
ويتضاعف الإحتمال ٢٢ مرة
if the defendant is black and the victim is white --
إذا كان المتهم أسود البشرة والضحية بيضاء البشرة --
in the very states where there are buried in the ground
في نفس الولايات التي دُفنت فيها تحت الأرض
the bodies of people who were lynched.
تلك الجثث للناس المُعدَمين.
And yet, there is this disconnect.
وبعد كل ذلك ، هناك تلك العُزلة.
Well I believe that our identity is at risk.
حسناً أعتقد بأن هويتنا في خطر.
That when we actually don't care
أنه عندما لا نهتم
about these difficult things,
بهذه الأمور المعقدة ،
the positive and wonderful things
فإن الأمور الإيجابية والجميلة
are nonetheless implicated.
تتلطخ بذلك.
We love innovation.
فنحن نحب الإبتكار.
We love technology. We love creativity.
نحب التكنولوجيا. نحب الإبداع.
We love entertainment.
نحب الترفيه.
But ultimately,
ولكن في النهاية ،
those realities
فإن هذه الأُمور
are shadowed by suffering,
تغلّفها المعاناة ،
abuse, degradation,
الإستغلال ، الإهانة ،
marginalization.
والتهميش.
And for me, it becomes necessary
وبالنسبة لي ، يصبح من الضروري
to integrate the two.
أن نوافق بين الإثنين.
Because ultimately we are talking
لأننا في النهاية نتحدث
about a need to be more hopeful,
عن الحاجة لأن نكون أكثر تفاؤلاً ،
more committed, more dedicated
ملتزمين أكثر ، ونكرس أنفسنا أكثر
to the basic challenges of living in a complex world.
للتحديات الأولية للعيش في عالمٍ أكثر تعقيداً.
And for me that means
وهذا يعني بالنسبة لي
spending time thinking and talking
قضاء وقتٍ أكبر في التفكير والتحدث
about the poor, the disadvantaged,
عن الفقراء ، المحرومين ،
those who will never get to TED.
أولائك الذين لن تتوفر لهم فرصة الحضور إلى تيد.
But thinking about them in a way
والتفكير بهم بطريقةٍ
that is integrated in our own lives.
تندمج في إطار حياتنا الخاصة.
You know ultimately, we all have to believe things we haven't seen.
تعلمون في النهاية ، إننا نؤمن بأشياء لم نراها من قبل.
We do. As rational as we are, as committed to intellect as we are.
بالفعل. فبقدر مانحن عقلانيون ، بقدر ما نحن ملتزمون بالحكمة.
Innovation, creativity,
الإبتكار ، الإبداع ،
development comes
و التطور لا يأتي فقط
not from the ideas in our mind alone.
من الأفكار في عقولنا.
They come from the ideas in our mind
إنها تأتي من الأفكار التي في عقولنا
that are also fueled
و التي تتغذى
by some conviction in our heart.
على إيمانٍ راسخ في قلوبنا.
And it's that mind-heart connection
وهو ذلك الإتصال بين العقل والقلب
that I believe compels us
الذي باعتقادي يرتقي بنا
to not just be attentive
لنكون مهتمين ليس فقط
to all the bright and dazzly things,
بالأشياء الرائعة والجميلة ،
but also the dark and difficult things.
ولكن أيضاً للأُمور المظلمة والصعبة.
Vaclav Havel, the great Czech leader, talked about this.
القائد التشيكي العظيم " فالكاف هافل" تحدث عن ذلك.
He said, "When we were in Eastern Europe and dealing with oppression,
وقال : "عندما كنا نعاني من الظلم في أوروبا الشرقية ،
we wanted all kinds of things,
كنا نريد أشياء شتى ،
but mostly what we needed was hope,
ولكن أكثر ما إحتجنا إليه كان هو الأمل ،
an orientation of the spirit,
الدافعٌ الروحي ،
a willingness to sometimes be in hopeless places
أن تكون في يومٍ ما في أماكن فقدت الأمل
and be a witness."
وأن تكون شاهداً على ذلك."
Well that orientation of the spirit
فإن الدافع الروحي
is very much at the core of what I believe
هو أساس كل ما أؤمن به
even TED communities
حتى جمهور تيد
have to be engaged in.
عليه أن يكون مشتركاً في ذلك.
There is no disconnect
ليس هناك فصل
around technology and design
بين التكنولوجيا والتصميم
that will allow us to be fully human
وبين أن نكون أكثر إنسانيةً
until we pay attention to suffering,
لنلتفت إلى المعاناة ،
to poverty, to exclusion, to unfairness, to injustice.
الفقر ، الإهمال ، الظلم ، وعدم المساواة.
Now I will warn you
والآن علي أن أحذركم
that this kind of identity
أن ذلك النوع من الهوية
is a much more challenging identity
تنطوي على تحدياتٍ أكثر
than ones that don't pay attention to this.
من غيرها التي لا تعير انتباهاً.
It will get to you.
وستؤثر فيكم.
I had the great privilege, when I was a young lawyer, of meeting Rosa Parks.
عندما كنت محامياً يافعاً ، كان لي الشرف في مقابلة "روزا باركس".
And Ms. Parks used to come back to Montgomery every now and then,
والسيدة باركس اعتادت أن تزور مونتغمري بين فترةٍ و أُخرى ،
and she would get together with two of her dearest friends,
وكانت تجتمع مع اثنين من أفضل صديقاتها ،
these older women,
وهؤلاء النسوة كنّ
Johnnie Carr who was the organizer
جوني كار والتي كانت منظمة
of the Montgomery bus boycott --
حركة مقاطعة باص مونتغمري --
amazing African-American woman --
كن نساءٍ مدهشاتٍ من أصولٍ أفريقية --
and Virginia Durr, a white woman,
و فيرجينيا دير ، امرأةً بيضاء ،
whose husband, Clifford Durr, represented Dr. King.
والتي كان زوجها "كليفورد دير" محامي الدكتور كينغ.
And these women would get together and just talk.
وهؤلاء النسوة كنّ يجتمعن ويتناقشون.
And every now and then Ms. Carr would call me,
وبين فترةٍ وأخرى ، كانت السيدة كار تتصل بي ،
and she'd say, "Bryan, Ms. Parks is coming to town. We're going to get together and talk.
وتقول : "بريان ، السيدة بارك قادمةٌ إلى المدينة. سنجتمع معاً ونتحادث.
Do you want to come over and listen?"
هل تود القدوم إلى هنا وتستمع ؟
And I'd say, "Yes, Ma'am, I do."
فأقول : "نعم ، سيدتي ، سأفعل ذلك."
And she'd say, "Well what are you going to do when you get here?"
فتقول: "حسناً ماذا ستفعل بعد قدومك إلى هنا ؟"
I said, "I'm going to listen."
قلت : "سأستمع."
And I'd go over there and I would, I would just listen.
وأذهب إلى هناك ، وأستمع فقط.
It would be so energizing and so empowering.
عادةً مايكون حديثهم محفزاً ومؤثراً.
And one time I was over there listening to these women talk,
وفي أحد المرات كنت أستمع إليهن يتحدثن ،
and after a couple of hours Ms. Parks turned to me
وبعد مايقارب الساعتين التفتت السيدة باركس نحوي
and she said, "Now Bryan, tell me what the Equal Justice Initiative is.
وقالت : "والآن بريان ، حدثني عن مشروعك المسمى بالعدالة المتساوية.
Tell me what you're trying to do."
أخبرني عما تحاول فعله."
And I began giving her my rap.
فبدأت أُعطيها ملخصي.
I said, "Well we're trying to challenge injustice.
وقلت :" حسناً نريد أن نتحدى الظلم.
We're trying to help people who have been wrongly convicted.
نريد مساعدة الأشخاص المتهمين بالخطأ.
We're trying to confront bias and discrimination
نريد أن نكافح التحيز والعنصرية
in the administration of criminal justice.
في إدارة العدالة والقضاء.
We're trying to end life without parole sentences for children.
نريد أن ننهي أحكام المؤبد بدون اطلاق سراح للأطفال.
We're trying to do something about the death penalty.
نريد أن نفعل شيئاً بشأن عقوبة الإعدام.
We're trying to reduce the prison population.
نريد أن نقلص من عدد المساجين.
We're trying to end mass incarceration."
نريد أن ننهي الإحتجاز بأعداد كبيرة.
I gave her my whole rap, and when I finished she looked at me
أعطيتها ملخصي كله ، وعندما انتهيت نظرت إلي
and she said, "Mmm mmm mmm."
وقالت : " هممم هممم هممم."
She said, "That's going to make you tired, tired, tired."
قالت : "هذا سيجعلك متعباً ، متعباً ، متعباً."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And that's when Ms. Carr leaned forward, she put her finger in my face,
وعندها مالت السيدة كار نحوي ، وأشارت بإصبعها إلى وجهي ،
she said, "That's why you've got to be brave, brave, brave."
وقالت : " ولهذا يجب عليك أن تكون شجاعاً ، شجاعاً ، شجاعاً."
And I actually believe that the TED community
وإنني أُؤمن بأن مجتمع تيد
needs to be more courageous.
يحتاج لأن يكون أكثر شجاعةً
We need to find ways
علينا أن نجد طرقاً
to embrace these challenges,
نتبنّى فيها تلك التحديات ،
these problems, the suffering.
نتبنى هذه المشكلات ، والمعاناة،
Because ultimately, our humanity depends
لأنه في النهاية ، إنسانيتنا تعتمد
on everyone's humanity.
على مدى إنسانية كل واحدٍ منا.
I've learned very simple things doing the work that I do.
لقد تعلمت الكثير من عملي.
It's just taught me very simple things.
فهو علمني الكثير من الأُمور البسيطة.
I've come to understand and to believe
لقد فهمت وأصبحت مؤمناً
that each of us
بأن كل واحدٍ منا
is more than the worst thing we've ever done.
يستحق ماهو أفضل من أي فعلٍ سيءٍ قد يكون قام به.
I believe that for every person on the planet.
وأُؤمن بذلك لكل شخصٍ على الأرض.
I think if somebody tells a lie, they're not just a liar.
وأعتقد بأنه لو كذب أحدهم مرةً ، لا يعني بأنه كاذبٌ مدى الحياة.
I think if somebody takes something that doesn't belong to them,
ولو أن أحدهم أخذ شيئاً ما ليس مِلكَهُ.
they're not just a thief.
فلا يعني ذلك أنه سارقٌ مدى الحياة.
I think even if you kill someone, you're not just a killer.
وأؤمن حتى لو أنك قتلت شخصاً ما ، فهذا لايعني بأنك قاتلٌ مدى الحياة.
And because of that there's this basic human dignity
ولهذا كله هناك أساسيات الكرامة الإنسانية
that must be respected by law.
والتي يجب أن يحترمها القانون.
I also believe
وأؤمن أيضاً
that in many parts of this country,
أنه في أماكن كثيرةٍ من هذا البلد ،
and certainly in many parts of this globe,
وبالتأكيد في مناطق كثيرة من هذا العالم ،
that the opposite of poverty is not wealth.
بأن عكس كلمة فقر ليس الثراء.
I don't believe that.
لا أُؤمن بهذا.
I actually think, in too many places,
بل أعتقد ، و في أماكن كثيرة ،
the opposite of poverty is justice.
بأن عكس كلمة فقر هو العدالة.
And finally, I believe
وأخيراً ، أؤمن بأنه
that, despite the fact that it is so dramatic
و بالرغم من كونه مسلياً
and so beautiful and so inspiring
وجميلاً جداً و مُلهماً جداً
and so stimulating,
ومؤثراً جداً ،
we will ultimately not be judged by our technology,
فإنه لن يُحكَم علينا في نهاية المطاف بتقنياتنا ،
we won't be judged by our design,
ولا بتصاميمنا ،
we won't be judged by our intellect and reason.
ولا بذكائنا و منطقنا.
Ultimately, you judge the character of a society,
ففي النهاية ، فإنك تحكم على شخصية المجتمع ،
not by how they treat their rich and the powerful and the privileged,
لا بطريقة معاملتهم للأغنياء و ذوي النفوذ والمؤهلين ،
but by how they treat the poor,
بل بطريقة معاملتهم للفقراء ،
the condemned, the incarcerated.
والمُذنبين ، والمحتجزين.
Because it's in that nexus
لأنه في ذلك التمازج فقط
that we actually begin to understand truly profound things
نبدأ بفهم أمور عميقةٍ بالفعل
about who we are.
عن من نكون.
I sometimes get out of balance. I'll end with this story.
في بعض الأحيان أفقد التركيز. سأُنهي بهذه القصة.
I sometimes push too hard.
أحياناً أكون متشدداً جداً.
I do get tired, as we all do.
بالفعل أتعب أحياناً ، مثل الجميع.
Sometimes those ideas get ahead of our thinking
أحياناً تلك الأفكار تسبق طريقة تفكيرنا
in ways that are important.
بطرقٍ مثيرة.
And I've been representing these kids
وكنت أترافع عن أولئك الأطفال
who have been sentenced to do these very harsh sentences.
الذين حُكم عليهم بأحكام قاسيةٍ جداً.
And I go to the jail and I see my client who's 13 and 14,
وعندما ذهبت إلى السجن وشاهدت أولئك الموكلين بعمر ال ١٣ و ١٤ ،
and he's been certified to stand trial as an adult.
وتم التصديق على محاكمتهم كبالغين.
I start thinking, well, how did that happen?
بدأت بالتفكير ، حسناً ، كيف حدث هذا ؟
How can a judge turn you into something
كيف يستطيع القاضي أن يحولك إلى
that you're not?
شخص آخر ؟
And the judge has certified him as an adult, but I see this kid.
وصدّق القاضي بأن يُحاكم كبالغ ، ولكنني أرى طفلاً.
And I was up too late one night and I starting thinking,
وكنت مستيقظاً لساعةٍ متأخرة وبدأت بالتفكير ،
well gosh, if the judge can turn you into something that you're not,
يا إلآهي ، إذا كان القاضي قادراً على تحويلك إلى شخص آخر ،
the judge must have magic power.
فلابد أن لدى القاضي قوةً خارقة.
Yeah, Bryan, the judge has some magic power.
حسناً ، بريان ، القاضي لديه قوى خارقة.
You should ask for some of that.
لابد أن تحصل على شيءٍ من ذلك.
And because I was up too late, wasn't thinking real straight,
ولأنني كنت مستيقظاً لوقتٍ متأخر ، لم أكن أفكر جيداً ،
I started working on a motion.
وبدأت العمل على مرافعة.
And I had a client who was 14 years old, a young, poor black kid.
وكان لدي موكلاً بعمر ١٤ سنة ، يافعاً ، طفلٌ أسود فقير.
And I started working on this motion,
وبدأت بكتابة تلك المرافعة ،
and the head of the motion was: "Motion to try my poor,
وكان عنوان المرافعة : " مرافعةٌ لمحاكمة موكلي ،
14-year-old black male client
الفقير ، الذكر ، الأسود بعمر ١٤ سنة
like a privileged, white 75-year-old
كأنه رجلٌ أبيض ، مدير تنفيذي ،
corporate executive."
بعمر ال ٧٥ سنة."
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And I put in my motion
وكتبت في مرافعتي
that there was prosecutorial misconduct and police misconduct and judicial misconduct.
بأنه كان هناك سوء تصرف من الإدعاء ، والشرطة ، والقضاء.
There was a crazy line in there about how there's no conduct in this county,
وكان هناك سطرٌ مجنون فيه يقول بأنه ليس هناك أي أخلاقيات في هذا البلد ،
it's all misconduct.
كان كل شيءٍ عبارة عن سوء تصرف.
And the next morning, I woke up and I thought, now did I dream that crazy motion,
وفي الصباح التالي ، استيقظت وفكرت ، هل كنت أحلم بتلك المرافعة المجنونة ،
or did I actually write it?
أم أنني كتبتها بالفعل ؟
And to my horror, not only had I written it,
ولدهشتي ، بإنني لم أكتبها فقط ،
but I had sent it to court.
بل أرسلتها إلى المحكمة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
A couple months went by,
ومرت بعض الشهور ،
and I had just forgotten all about it.
ونسيت كل شيءٍ عنها.
And I finally decided,
وأخيراً قررت ،
oh gosh, I've got to go to the court and do this crazy case.
ياإلآهي ، علي الذهاب إلى المحكمة والمرافعة بتلك القضية المجنونة.
And I got into my car
وركبت سيارتي
and I was feeling really overwhelmed -- overwhelmed.
وشعرت بأنني كنت أتجاوز الحد -- تجاوزت الحد.
And I got in my car and I went to this courthouse.
واتجهت بسيارتي إلى قاعة المحكمة.
And I was thinking, this is going to be so difficult, so painful.
وكنت أفكر ، سيكون ذلك صعباً ، ومؤلماً جداً.
And I finally got out of the car and I started walking up to the courthouse.
وأخيراً ترجلت من سيارتي واتجهت إلى قاعة المحكمة.
And as I was walking up the steps of this courthouse,
وعندما اقتربت من قاعة المحكمة ،
there was an older black man who was the janitor in this courthouse.
كان هناك رجلٌ أسود كبير السن والذي كان الحاجب في تلك المحكمة.
When this man saw me, he came over to me
وعندما رآني ، أتى إلي فوراً
and he said, "Who are you?"
وقال : " من تكون ؟"
I said, "I'm a lawyer." He said, "You're a lawyer?" I said, "Yes, sir."
فقلت : " أنا محامي." وقال: " هل أنت محامي؟" ، قلت: "نعم ، سيدي."
And this man came over to me
فاقترب مني ذلك الرجل
and he hugged me.
وعانقني.
And he whispered in my ear.
و همس في أُذني.
He said, "I'm so proud of you."
وقال: " إنني فخورٌ جداً بك."
And I have to tell you,
ويجب أن أقول لكم ،
it was energizing.
بأنها كانت مُحفّزة.
It connected deeply with something in me
ولامست في داخلي شيئاً
about identity,
عن الهوية ،
about the capacity of every person to contribute
عن قدرة كل شخص في المساهمة
to a community, to a perspective that is hopeful.
في المجتمع ، بطريقةٍ تبعث بالأمل.
Well I went into the courtroom.
حسناً إتجهت إلى قاعة المحكمة.
And as soon as I walked inside, the judge saw me coming in.
وعندما دخلت القاعة و رآني القاضي قادماً.
He said, "Mr. Stevenson, did you write this crazy motion?"
قال: "السيد ستيفنسن ، هل أنت من كتب هذه المرافعة الحمقاء؟"
I said, "Yes, sir. I did." And we started arguing.
فقلت :"نعم ، سيدي. أنا فعلت ذلك." وبدأنا في المجادلة.
And people started coming in because they were just outraged.
وبدأ الناس يتوافدون لأنهم كانوا غاضبين.
I had written these crazy things.
بسبب كتابتي لتلك الأشياء المثيرة.
And police officers were coming in
وكان ضباط الشرطة يتوافدون
and assistant prosecutors and clerk workers.
ومساعدي الإدعاء العام والموظفين.
And before I knew it, the courtroom was filled with people
وقبل أن أُلاحظ ذلك ، إمتلأت قاعة المحكمة بالناس
angry that we were talking about race,
الغاضبين في أننا نتحدث عن العنصرية ،
that we were talking about poverty,
في أننا نتحدث عن الفقر ،
that we were talking about inequality.
ونتحدث عن عدم المساواة.
And out of the corner of my eye, I could see this janitor pacing back and forth.
واستطعت بطرف عيني لمح حاجب المحكمة يخطوا جيئةً وذهاباً.
And he kept looking through the window, and he could hear all of this holler.
وكان ينظر من خلال النافذة ، ويستطيع سماع الصوت المرتفع.
He kept pacing back and forth.
واستمر في المشي جيئةً وذهاباً.
And finally, this older black man with this very worried look on his face
وأخيراً ، جاء ذلك الحاجب الأسود وفي وجهه علامات القلق
came into the courtroom and sat down behind me,
وجلس في قاعة المحكمة بالقرب مني ،
almost at counsel table.
وكأنه مستشار المحامي.
About 10 minutes later the judge said we would take a break.
وبعد عشر دقائق ، أمر القاضي بأخذ استراحة.
And during the break there was a deputy sheriff who was offended
و في فترة الإستراحة كان هناك نائب الشريف والذي شعر ببعض الإهانة
that the janitor had come into court.
من أن حاجب المحكمة يجلس بداخل القاعة.
And this deputy jumped up and he ran over to this older black man.
فنهض ذلك النائب واتجه فوراً لذلك الرجل المسن الأسود.
He said, "Jimmy, what are you doing in this courtroom?"
وقال: "جيمي ، مالذي تفعله بقاعة المحكمة هذه ؟"
And this older black man stood up
فوقف ذلك الرجل المسن الأسود
and he looked at that deputy and he looked at me
ونظر لذلك النائب ثم نظر إلي
and he said, "I came into this courtroom
وقال : " قدمت لقاعة المحكمة هذه
to tell this young man,
لأخبر هذا الرجل اليافع ،
keep your eyes on the prize, hold on."
إبق الهدف نصب عينيك ، واصبر."
I've come to TED
لقد قدمت إلى تيد
because I believe that many of you understand
لأنني أؤمن بأن الكثير منكم يفهم
that the moral arc of the universe is long,
أن الإنحناء الأخلاقي للكون طويلٌ جداً ،
but it bends toward justice.
ولكنه يتجه نحو العدالة.
That we cannot be full evolved human beings
وأننا لن نكون بشراً مكتملين التطور
until we care about human rights and basic dignity.
حتى نهتم بحقوق البشر والكرامة الإنسانية.
That all of our survival
وأن استمرار بقائنا جميعاً
is tied to the survival of everyone.
يعتمد على بقاء كل فردٍ منا.
That our visions of technology and design
وأن رؤيتنا للتكنولوجيا والتصميم
and entertainment and creativity
والترفيه والإبداع
have to be married with visions
عليها أن تتزاوج مع رؤيتنا
of humanity, compassion and justice.
للإنسانية ، والتعاطف ، والعدالة.
And more than anything,
وأكثر من أي شيءٍ آخر ،
for those of you who share that,
لاؤلئك الذين يشاطرونني في هذا ،
I've simply come to tell you
أتيت لأقول لكم ببساطة
to keep your eyes on the prize, hold on.
أبقوا الهدف نصب عينيكم ، اصبروا.
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Chris Anderson: So you heard and saw
كريس أندرسون: إذاً لقد سمعت ورأيت
an obvious desire by this audience, this community,
رغبةً واضحة من هذا الجمهور ، هذا التجمع ،
to help you on your way and to do something on this issue.
لمساعدتك في فعل شيءٍ ما على طريقتك.
Other than writing a check,
غير كتابة شيك فقط ،
what could we do?
ماذا بإمكاننا فعله ؟
BS: Well there are opportunities all around us.
ب.س: حسناً هناك فرص في كل مكان.
If you live in the state of California, for example,
إذا كنتم تعيشون في ولاية كاليفورنيا ، على سبيل المثال ،
there's a referendum coming up this spring
هناك إستفتاءٌ في الربيع القادم
where actually there's going to be an effort
حيث هناك محاولات
to redirect some of the money we spend on the politics of punishment.
لتحويل جزءٍ من الأموال المصروفة في قوانين العقوبات
For example, here in California
على سبيل المثال ، هنا في كاليفورنيا
we're going to spend one billion dollars
سنصرف مليار دولاراً
on the death penalty in the next five years --
لمصاريف عقوبة الإعدام للسنوات الخمس القادمة --
one billion dollars.
مليار دولار.
And yet, 46 percent of all homicide cases
بالرغم من أنه ، ٤٦٪ من جرائم القتل
don't result in arrest.
لا تؤدي إلى أي اعتقال.
56 percent of all rape cases don't result.
٥٦٪ من جرائم الإغتصاب لا يتم حلها.
So there's an opportunity to change that.
وهناك فرصةٌ لتغيير كل هذا.
And this referendum would propose having those dollars
وهذا الإستفتاء يقترح صرف تلك الدولارات
go to law enforcement and safety.
لدوائر تطبيق القانون والأمن.
And I think that opportunity exists all around us.
وأعتقد أن هذه الفرصة متاحةٌ للجميع.
CA: There's been this huge decline
ك.أ.: كان هناك انخفاض شديد
in crime in America over the last three decades.
في معدل الجريمة في أمريكا في الثلاثين سنةً الأخيرة.
And part of the narrative of that
وجزءٌ من تلك الحكاية
is sometimes that it's about increased incarceration rates.
هو أحياناً ازديادٌ في معدل عدد المساجين.
What would you say to someone who believed that?
ماذا تقول لشخص مقتنعٍ بذلك ؟
BS: Well actually the violent crime rate
ب.س.: حسناً إن معدل جرائم العنف
has remained relatively stable.
لايزال هو نفسه.
The great increase in mass incarceration in this country
والإزدياد في معدل المساجين في هذا البلد
wasn't really in violent crime categories.
لم يكن فعلياً بسبب جرائم العنف.
It was this misguided war on drugs.
بل كانت تلك الحملات الغير موجهة جيداً على المخدرات.
That's where the dramatic increases have come
تلك كانت أسباب الزيادة
in our prison population.
في تعداد المساجين.
And we got carried away with the rhetoric of punishment.
واستمرينا في المبالغة في أنواع العقوبات.
And so we have three strikes laws
لذا فإنه لدينا ثلاثة قوانين صارمة
that put people in prison forever
تضع الناس في السجن المؤبد.
for stealing a bicycle, for low-level property crimes,
لمجرد سرقة دراجة ، وجرائم الملكية البسيطة ،
rather than making them give those resources back
بدلاً من أن نجبرهم على إعادة تلك الملكيات
to the people who they victimized.
لأصحابها الضحايا.
I believe we need to do more to help people who are victimized by crime,
علينا فعل المزيد لأولائك الذين تضرروا من تلك الجرائم ،
not do less.
ولا نكتفي بالأقل.
And I think our current punishment philosophy
وأعتقد أن فلسفتنا في العقاب الآن
does nothing for no one.
لاتفعل أي شيء لأي أحد.
And I think that's the orientation that we have to change.
وأعتقد أن ذلك التفكير هو مايجب أن نغيره.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
CA: Bryan, you've struck a massive chord here.
ك.أ.: بريان ، لقد أصبت وتراً حساساً لدينا.
You're an inspiring person.
أنت بالفعل شخصٌ مؤثر.
Thank you so much for coming to TED. Thank you.
وأشكرك على قدومك إلى تيد . شكراً لك.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)